Hey guys, Shandid welcome back to the
channel and today in micros service
topic we are going to cover load
balancer. So let's start without wasting
any time. So we all know what load
balancer is. Generally it helps in
distributing the traffic to multiple
instances of a server, right? Which
helps in preventing single server from
being overloaded with huge traffic. This
is very very basic definition of load
balancer which we all know. But things
got more interesting when we go into its
type. So generally it's of two type.
Serverside load balancer and client side
load balancer. So in serverside load
balancer what generally happen is it has
centralized load balancer. Right? So
here if you see this is your client.
Let's say this is our spring boot app.
This is our spring boot app which we
have written. Now we are calling a
dedicated you can say that uh server
which do the role of load balancing. So
it has a centralized load balancer.
Okay. So our client do not contains any
logic of load balancing. Okay. So it
calls a dedicated load balancer server
which does and forward the request to
one of the service requested service.
But in the client side load balancer
what generally happen is load balancing
capability present inside the client the
caller itself. Okay. So here if you see
this is what we are doing today and this
is what we have done in the service
discovery if you remember. So this is
our spring boot application which we
have developed let's say. So what it
does it first invokes service discovery.
Let's say it say that hey give me all
the instances of service A. Now service
discovery return the list of all the
possible instances available for the
service A. Now this client holds the
logic of the load balancing. Either it
could be a library or either it return
its own logic but client has the logic.
Client does the load balancing and pass
the request to one of the server.
Okay. So that's the difference between
serverside load balancing and client
side load balancing. And this is what we
are going to cover client side load
balancer. Serverside load balancer when
we cover API gateway engine X right so
that time we can cover it. Okay.
So
client side load balancers is something
which we are going to see. So the
prerequisite is the service discovery
because if you remember in the service
discovery when we use fain client right
in the flank client it automatically
it automatically
internally uses load balancer in case of
service discovery. Okay. So we have to
know the service discovery before we
start with the load balancer. So that's
a prerequisite you can check in the
playlist.
So let's start with the client side load
balancing with rest template because if
you understand the rest template then
for either rest client f client web
client whatever you are going to do the
load balancing logic would be same it
not going to differ.
So in service discovery topic previous
video we have seen that after we have
set the service discovery the rest
template we fetch the list of instances
using discovery client object. We have
already seen that right and then client
is manually choosing the instances from
the list and invoking the endpoint. See
if you can recall from the previous
video service uh discovery one. So I'm
showing you an example of rest template.
not faint line. Okay. So in the rest
template if you remember we were first
creating the object of rest template
inside a configuration which we have
autowired it. Okay. Now here if you see
we are using an object of discovery
client. With discovery client we are
fetching the instances of this service
product service from Ureka server. Hey
Ureka server give me all the instances
of this product servers. Once you get it
and here if you see this is we were
choosing like you can say that this is a
very bad uh load balancing algorithm. We
were always picking get zero but this is
just an example that hey after you get
all the instances we have to have a load
balancing logic and we have to pick one
instance and call it. Okay, use that
host and port number.
Okay, so if you can recall this one here
we haven't used any load balancing
capability now. Okay, so here we are
fetching it. We are writing our
capability and we are then invoking a
particular server. So we can use a
spring cloud load balancer which is a
spring cloud load balancer is your
clientside
load balancer. Okay. So spring cloud
load balancer there are more uh client
side load balancer like Netflix reborn
which is I think deprecated now it's
deprecated.
So spring cloud load balancer is
something which is frequently used and
stto uh service mesh that is also very
frequently used. Okay. So we can use any
of the client side load balancer which
we want.
So now here if you see
if we have to use the uh spring cloud
load balancer into the above this rest
template what we can do the first thing
first we have to add in dependency of
the load balancer spring cloud load
balancer cap uh dependency we have to
add in our pom. Okay. Now the second
thing is
we have to annotate where we are
creating an object of rest template we
have to annotate with at the rate load
balanced. Why? Because this annotation
tells the framework that hey intercept
the request intercept the request and
call service discovery get an instance
and apply load balancing algorithm. So
there is something called load balancer
interceptor.
Load balancer interceptor. So this class
will get invoked. Okay. So this is the
purpose of this annotation. It tells the
framework that add this interceptor.
Okay. We will see that. So this is one
thing is we have to annotate our rest
template with this annotation. Another
difference you will see that earlier we
were using discovery discovery client
right now you don't need discovery
client itself because this interceptor
internally
will call service discovery fetch an
instances do load balancing and call one
server.
Okay. So you don't manually need to do
that. All you have to do that is just
provide the name of the service which
you have to invoke. Okay. So I have
written into the application.properties
that http product hyphen service. Now I
am not using let's say 192.80.60.3
hey call 8082. I am not using the
hardcoded host and port number right. I
have just invoked that hey product
service this is the name of the service
I have given into the application like
here for this order application I have
given the name order I order hyphen
service right similarly for the product
service I have given that name so I'm
using that name which service you are
going to invoke
okay so the same here this is the URL
okay so this http colon product service
and this is the URI
relative path which we have to invoke.
Now this
will get resolved by our load balancer.
Okay. So now here if you see lot of
things become simpler for us. Okay. We
just have added the dependency and just
uh tell through this annotation that
intercept intercept the request and use
load balancer interceptor. Now here we
don't have to do
the calling of the service direct uh
service discovery we don't have to put
an algorithm for choosing one of the
particular service all internally got
handled but the question should comes to
you now how what algorithm how we can
change it that's we going to see it okay
so if you face any doubt with the rest
template like hey you are not able to
understand this. So I would say that
like please go through this rest
template first right and I even I have
shown the in-depth of this rest template
framework how the control flows whenever
we do this one right get for object in
the rest template what exactly happened
I have already explained in depth so the
thing is once you put this at the rate
load balance annotation so in this
framework I am just assuming that you
have already seen the rest template
video and you know this how internally
it works. So in the rest template flow
when when we used to call the execute
method that's where the interception
works and that's where first this will
get invoked load balancer interceptor do
java at this point of time. Okay. So
before execution of this first this
interceptor now get invoked. Now here if
you see if you debug this interceptor
code you will see this piece of code
where it try to does this two thing.
So first it does load balancer client
factory get instance for this service
ID. What it does it will pick the load
balancing algorithm for you.
It will pick the load balancing
algorithm like a roundroin or random
whatever. So it will pick one load
balancing algorithm for you first. Okay.
After that it calls load balancer dot
choose request. So internally it calls
service discovery.
Pick one instance based on the above
load balancing algorithm. So internally
it calls service discovery. Get a list
of instance and whatever the load
balancer algorithm you have got using
that it will pick one instance of it.
Okay. So all this code logic is present
inside this interceptor.
Okay. So there are different types of
algorithms present into load balancing.
Like I have already covered into this
HLD playlist. If you go into the HLD
playlist, you will see I think around
18th video like we have discussed a lot
of algorithm round robin, least
connection, IP hash, least response
time, random. So I am not going to cover
what exactly the algorithm does that is
already present into the HL playlist.
But today our main purpose is to
understand that how framework does it.
Okay. So if you see this line again
where it picks the load balancing
algorithm. This is very very important.
We have to understand it better because
remember when you are about to code it I
am pretty much sure you will face lot of
challenge because of this service ID
because of the service ID. So understand
this service ID concept properly. This
going to help you when you write it.
Right. This is I from based on my
experience I'm telling you lot of
engineers get stuck this how it's
working okay so we will look at this
little bit better where this line
choosing the load balancer for us it
will choosing the load balancer right
for us so one thing question comes to
our mind is what is this service ID
getting passed okay and what its purpose
Why and what its purpose? So one thing
is this service ID is nothing but a
client ID or you can say that client
name. So here in this case say like a
product service is also known as service
ID. Let's say order service. This is my
application name right at you can say
that ureka server we have used this
application names. So these are known as
service ID. Okay. So each why we are
passing this client name or service ID
to this load balancer
remember that
each load balancer algorithm is attached
to a service ID. So now let's say that
this is your application. Just
understand that this is your
application.
Now you have a dependency on product.
You have a dependency on sales.
You have a dependency on some XY Z
application. Okay. So I have given its
name product
service. I have given it a name sales -
service. Similarly XY Z - service some
something something. So these are the
application name. Remember that load
balancing algorithm is for attached to a
specific service. So for this service I
am using round robin. For this service I
am attaching it with random.
For this service I am attaching it with
let's say weighted algorithm. So
whatever the algorithm of a load
balancer is attached to a particular
service
always.
Okay.
So this going to help us very this is
the main concept actually we will see
that when we will override it right this
is where the challenge comes that hey
how why this product service is
important it is important because
whatever the algorithm we are picking
load balancing algorithm it's attached
to one of the service it's not like I
choose uh round robin now it's roundroin
is for product service also sales
service also this also no It's always
get attached to one of the service.
Okay. So we will see that more but at
this point of only this thing keep in at
the back of your mind that yes whatever
the load balancing algorithm we are
picking it is attached to one of the
service.
Okay. So each load balancing algorithm
is attached to a service ID. Service ID
is nothing but a client name like
product service.
By default, Spring Cloud load balancer
picks round robin load balancer. So this
is the default load balancer algorithm.
We can change it for a specific service
for all the service also. We will see
that how. But this is the by default for
all the service. Okay. No matter how
many service you add for all the service
round robin get attached. Round robin
for product service, roundroin for sales
service, roundroin for XY Z service.
Okay. So for each service roundroin load
balancer is the default algorithm is
chosen.
So
if we are not going with default
algorithm, if you don't want to go with
roundroin, then we need to define for
which client or service ID which
algorithm we need. Again it's just a
different way of saying that each
algorithm load balancing algorithm is
attached to a particular service ID. So
we have to tell okay you don't want to
go with roundroin what algorithm you
want to choose but for which service we
have to tell the both
a spring cloud load balancer
supports only two algorithm roundroin
and random
okay so here this is the class hierarchy
if you see that
this is one of the load balancer round
robin load balancer and this is the
another random load balancer we can if
you need more or different you can
create a child class you write a custom
load balancer and use it. We will see
that how we can do that. Okay. So but by
default only two algorithms are present
into the spring cloud load balancer
round robin and random. If you want
different algorithm like weighted lease
connection then we need to write either
custom or we need to use different uh
library maybe stto with sidecar it has
wide variety of algorithms present
inside it sidecar
okay
so
now your requirement is that hey we want
to use random load balancer I don't want
to use round robin we want to use random
how we can override it.
So very very simple. Okay, this is same
like uh the configuration I am just
creating an object of rest template and
while creating a rest template object I
have annotated with add the rate load
balance so that my load balancer uh
interceptor can catch it and here
exactly same like uh no difference while
invoking it in the
application.properties properties no
difference I have provided the base URL
which is this here I'm using the service
name now the difference which comes in
that first
in your application let's say this is my
order application in the order service
application we have to put load balancer
client annotation okay in this load
balancer client annotation we tell that
hey for this service product service
this is the configuration which we have
to use okay so this is very very
specific for the load balancer
okay so now here if you see I have
provided a load balancer product client
config load balancer product client this
is very very specific
just see it red again load balancer
client this client is for name is
product service so I am writing this
config very very specific for this
product service very very specific for
this product service okay so I have
written this configuration and now here
if you see I am creating reactor load
balancer so I am creating from this
hierarchy you know that all this rand
round robin random these are the
hierarchy so it returns the object of
this one reactor load balancer okay
So I am returning now random load
balancer.
I am returning now random load balancer.
But slowly understand it what exactly
happened. So first by first
let's start it from here.
This config this load balancer product
client config is different from this
normal config class. Here I have created
this uh configuration class. Right? You
already understand that when you start
an application, when you start an
application, what would happen is this
bean will get created at the time of
startup. Correct?
This is different. This configuration is
lazy. This configuration is different.
Load balancer configuration is
different. the configuration again I'm
saying the configuration which is
associated with load balancer client is
different from the normal config class
because normal config class like above
where we are creating an object of rest
template right like this
get invokes at application startup only
all the beans will get created but this
load balancer client config right this
load balancer config whatever you will
define the config here for the load
balancer invokes at runtime two.
So whenever you are going to invoke this
right http colon product service some
relative path whenever you are trying to
invoke this endpoint product service at
that point of time this configuration
will invoke also
okay at that point of time it will
decide what is the load balancing
algorithm you are picking
why I will tell you the reason for it
also when we
go for the global. Okay, but remember
this, this is very important.
This config differs from the normal
config because this configuration load
balancer configuration
invokes at runtime two. Okay, so that is
first part. The second part is now here
if you see when I am creating a random
load balancer this random load balancer
constructor takes two
parameter one is service instance list
supplier another is service ID. Okay. So
now here this is the this will return me
an object of service instance list
supplier this one. So what is the use of
this service instance list supplier?
This object service instance list
supplier is actually the one which helps
to invoke the service discovery. So
using this object using this supplier
object service instance list supplier
using this object we invoke the service
discovery. Okay. And for what uh what
name what server we have to ask for
instance is this one product service. So
that's what it it gives us a lazy object
means it's not call now okay whenever we
call it whenever we required it then
only its object will provide it to us.
So it give us an object lazily that's
what generally it does. So the first
thing it does is it provides an object
of the service instance list supplier.
Using this we will invoke service
discovery
for which instance this instance product
service. Now the second is this product
hyphen service. Why we need this? I told
you each load balancing algorithm. Here
I am picking random load balancer is
associated with a particular service ID
or client name. So that's where so this
random load balancer is now associated
with this service ID. Only when you are
invoking this product hyphen service
then only random load balancer is used
otherwise it is not used.
Okay.
So again very simple uh we have to first
annotate it with in your application
load balancer client annotation
we will provide a name for which service
which configuration has to look for. So
product hyphen service go for this
configuration. Okay then here we have
defined that which load balancing
algorithm has to be used. Okay,
that's all. Okay, so this is only we
need it. But now the question comes is
what if for product service I want
algorithm A for
order - service I want something XY Z
algo and for all I want algorithm B.
Okay. What I'm trying to say is that
what if you have different different
requirement. Let's say for service one I
want algo A.
For service 2 I want algo B. But for all
of the service 3, service 4, service 5,
I want some default elgo. Default lo
balancing algo same for all. How we can
do that? Again very simple the same
thing. Now we have one more annotation
called load balancer clients
not earlier it was client
client now we have is clients so the
client here has two parts one is default
configuration okay and another is inside
a value we can provide comma separated
different load balancer client so now
let's say that one I have provided
similarly at the rate load balance
balancer client for product service.
This is the configuration. Similarly,
comma separated you can put load
balancer client name order service what
is the configuration you want to put
give it. Okay. So different different
configuration we can give for different
different service if required different
algorithm because here I can use random
algorithm for order service I can in
this configuration I can use some
different algorithm for rest of the
service I want default right so what is
the default configuration I want to use
let's say this is the load balancer
global config plus
okay so this is the first place where we
have to define that for Each service one
what is the algo? Algo is generally
defined in a configuration class. So for
service one what is a configuration
class? For service two what is a
configuration class? And default what
are the configuration. Okay. So this is
the first thing.
So now here if you see that
I will tell you the first the global
config this default one right? default
one I will tell you.
So now here if you see this is first
part and in this global configuration
what we want to do is you recall one
part one is each
for each product or each service ID like
a product service order service no
matter how many service you have in your
application which you are dependent on a
sales service
like for each one
for each one load balancer algorithm
would be mapped what algorithm have to
be created okay so now here if you see
that now let's say that for product
service I have already defined that go
for this load balancer product client so
this is the first first child client
config will load it then the default one
so it has an order so First all the
childs if there are more child load
balancer client that bean will get
created. After that the default one will
get created. Okay. So now let's say that
for product service it goes to this
particular load balancer product client
config. Okay. There it's we have already
seen that how we can attach a particular
algorithm to a product service. But now
let's say for these two I want
common algorithm like a default or even
if I have more XY Z service for all
these three my service I need one common
algorithm one common algorithm for this
one so
while defining while defining a new
roundroin load balancer I told you that
it's attached with the particular
service ID
Now this is dynamic right
we have order service we have sales
service we have XYZ service we can't
hardcode it at this place we can't
hardcode it right it's it is dynamic at
runtime that is one of the reason if you
remember I told you all the load
balancer configuration
loads at runtime like which service you
are invoking
okay now let's say that you are invoking
order - service at runtime. So at
runtime from the environment it will get
a property name. So this is will give
you the service ID dynamically.
And now like similarly I can create an
object of a roundroin load balancer like
whatever the algorithm you want to pick
I can create a roundroin load balancer
algorithm and I can put a service ID. I
don't have to hardcode it now. Okay. So
I put a service ID and this is the same
here service ID used which is used for
service discovery that hey use this
call the service discovery for this
service ID.
Okay. Now when you are trying to invoke
sales service
with this dynamic runtime it will get a
context get this config invoke this.
Now this service ID would be salesy
service. Now this algorithm now also
attached with this service ID also. So
for each service ID
it will have this bean.
Okay.
So this is how global configuration we
can write. Okay. Now you can ask that
hey why you have put at the rate
conditional on missing beam.
Remember that
here if you see at top
we have
one global config. We have a global
global config in which we are
dynamically finding out a service ID.
Okay. And then we are creating a round
robin load balancer algo and attach that
service ID with that and we have one
product hyphen service also in that
configuration we we hardcoded it service
ID because it's specific for product
service but there we are creating a
random load balancer algo.
So we have to we have to make
sure that duplicate product service is
not created. So at runtime now let's say
you are trying to invoke http colon
product
service.
Okay at this point of time now we have
two configuration two load balancer
configuration. One is global and one is
specific for product.
Okay. So I told you that the first
priority is for the internal one the
child one before it goes to the global.
So first it will get invoked this
configuration will get invoked and when
this configuration will get invoked it
will create a load balancer algorithm
and tied with the product service.
Now after that internal according to the
ordering now global will get invoke. Now
dynamically if you see that dynamically
it will find out it's a product hyphen
service and it will try to create a
roundroin algo. So for one service two
algo will get attached and you will get
an exception runtime exception. So to
avoid that runtime exception we have to
add that and we have to tell that hey if
already a load balancer algorithm is
chosen for a particular product service
ID don't go inside it that's all.
Okay, this is required in the global
because we have a specific
configuration for the particular service
and we don't want that in the global
also its load balancer get created or
get mapped. So we have to tell
okay only in case of missing bean go
inside it. If bean is already present
for that product service don't go don't
go inside it.
Okay so product service already got run
and we have already seen that for
product service we are using random load
balancer and we have hardcoded it. We
know that it is specific for product but
in the global we can't hardcode it
right. So that's why we are using this
environment and you already know that
why it's uh load balancer configs are
run at runtime. Maybe at runtime this is
not much helpful because uh during
application startup we know product
hyphen service is present is this is the
service but for global
this is important because we can't
hardcode it. So at runtime we need to
know which service we are trying to
invoke and for that service it creates a
load balancer algorithm.
Okay. So now question next come is what
if you want to write your own custom
load balancer. You don't want to use
roundroin. You don't want to use random.
You want to write your own custom logic.
So if you understand this hierarchy like
these are interfaces reactive load
balancer reactor load balancer reactor
service instance load balancer and these
are the concrete classes round robin and
random so we have to create a child
custom load balancer just in inside this
okay and we have to provide an
implementation of this choose method
so that's what I did so here I provide
my custom load balancer
created a child of reactor service
instance load balancer. This one child
of this. Okay. And here I have a
constructor. The constructor take two
part like we have seen like in here if
you see like new round robin load
balancer. It this does constructor take
two parts. One is your service instance
list supplier object and another is
service ID. the same thing the
constructor which require service
instance supplier and the service id and
we have to provide an implementation of
the choose so this is where what it does
so this is the first
using this object service instance
supplier I am doing get if available
internally it will call service
discovery
once you get the instances for each
instance
okay like H you can do an load balancing
algorithm. If instances are not null so
here if instances are present we have to
pick one of the instance. So we can
write custom algorithm here. So
currently I'm picking only first
instance get zero but you can write your
custom algorithm.
Okay. So this is the choose method which
does this thing. Okay. So round robin
you can uh debug the choose roundroin.
Go to the roundrobin load balancer class
check its choose. So it first does the
same thing get if available which calls
the service discovery you get the
instances and for those instances you
are doing a roundrobing algorithm
performing in random it just called
random method. Now if you write a custom
logic in after you get the instances if
you got zero instances you return empty
response or throw exception. If you got
the instances pick one instance based on
your algorithm.
Now once you have written this now let's
say that for product service I want to
use this algorithm how to do that we
know right in the
first in this application startup we
have put load balancer client give name
equals to product service and whatever
the configuration is this okay in our
application order service application
and inside the config load balancer
product config we can now tell that hey
this is the load balancer use this the
first one is we have to runtime during
runtime right so we have to provide an
object here and the service
so you got it right so this is how
internally the load balancing happens
you can write your custom load balancer
you want or by default is round robin
you can change it to random to a
particular service or to all the
service. The major major major problems
or difficulty comes into the global only
global and perk config. We only have to
understand the importance of service ID
because these configs runs at runtime
when you actually from your service when
you are actually invoking product
service or sales service at that time
the particular ser uh config get
invoked.
Okay. So that is important and you can
change the algorithm which you want. I
have already told you you can uh know
that if global and specific configs are
present you make you have to make sure
that
uh duplicate uh for one product service
or one service two algorithm is not uh
created. So we have to also handle that.
So once you understand this rest
template
you can even the f client rest client
is using the same load balancing
interceptor only no change at all. So if
you recall from the service discovery
video right if you recall for the fing
client service discovery I told you that
we have to add a load balancer also
because internally fing framework
does the same thing okay because it once
you get a multiple instances it has to
pick one instance right so it use a load
balancer
okay so for fink client we don't have to
do anything whatever the service
discovery we have to do it's the same
thing right now
see this one like I I'm hoping that you
have seen the service discovery video
and you can correlate this like without
service discovery in the f client we
have to provide the URL
but with service discovery we have to
only give the name hey I want only
product service
that's all okay and we just invoke it.
Now let's say that if you want to change
the algorithm you don't want faint
client to use by default you know that
internally if it's using a load balancer
it might be using round robin you want
that hey I don't want round robin I want
some different algorithm can you even if
you are using faint client can you
change it now easily same in the
application
if it is only one client then you can
use load balancer client provide a name
service this for this service this
configuration have to be use I have
written this configuration which will
get also get invoked at runtime when I'm
going to invoke this service get product
by ID.
So here I just changed the load
balancing algorithm new load balancer
okay and attach it with this service ID.
Okay. Now if you go inside this load
balancer choose method
this choose method for that one that
internally it will do what we did first
call service discovery and then it will
randomly pick one of the time
the same thing.
Okay. So even though everything is
abstracted from us in case of fain and
even in case of rest template we only
have to use this annotation
at the rate load balance
and everything is got abstracted
under the load balancer interceptor.
is still better. It's better to
understand this little framework so that
in any scenario if an interviewer or you
are in company use case come that you
have to write your own load balancing
logic or for one of the service you have
to change the load balancing capability.
How you can do that?
Okay. So play with this. Okay. Play with
this config. put a debugger point here
that uh system.out.printland
put something that I am inside this run
it during application startup. So during
application startup you will see and at
the time of
actual invoking the service that time
also you will see that it will get
invoked.
Okay
and I already told you again it's
runtime uh functionality is very
important for the global part because in
global this service ID has to be run
dynamically because during application
startup this would be null because we
haven't invoked anything. So this
roundroin load balancer algorithm would
get tied up to null service ID. Okay. So
at runtime when you are calling product
hyphen service again this got called.
Okay. And that time this service ID is
got set and then this roundroin is also
get mapped to product service. Okay. And
once it is mapped now no matter you call
100 time product service it will not
call again only one time. till its bean
has to be created load balancer bean.
Okay.
So hope this uh give you a little bit
insight on lo how spring framework
handles the load balancing capability
and
I hope this something you will find
useful. If you find it uh helpful please
u do comment out or if there is doubt
please put into the comment section. We
can discuss further. Thank you. Bye.